[SPEAKER_02]: So, what was your question, eh?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you repeat it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, my question was that, see, I've been practicing meditation and I hear about meditations.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've done two different techniques, but when you say meditation, I don't really know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even when I do it, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just do it, but if it's the proper way I'm doing it, if I'm just deluding myself, it's just...
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, one thing to get out of the way is, only a sotāpanna can meditate properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is no sama-samādhi without sama-dhīti.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, coming from that point of view, you can see how silly the idea of a technique is, that you can teach to others, whereby they just emulate and mechanically repeat it.
[SPEAKER_02]: kind of leads automatically to wisdom or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: It leads to an experience of novelty of a kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, again, in connection to what I said a half an hour ago, previous recording was,
[SPEAKER_02]: Repeating something thousands of times rightly, based on your discernment, based on your faith, you know that this, attending things like this, is most likely right, so you repeat, repeat, repeat, repeat it thousands of times, and then you get a confirmation, you get wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: You discern, oh, it is right, what I've been doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, getting a template technique, that can somehow lead you to that right state,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's rather... well, it's obvious that it's kind of impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if I tell you a technique that works for everyone and everything, it doesn't mean that... it doesn't require you to be discerning anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just requires you to repeat these observances and these procedures that I've described for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Observe the nostrils when this happens, you do that, when you do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not about
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, understanding is not broad about doing certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll tell you, you will understand, you will gain knowledge, if you're mindful of your shoulders, and you watch your breath in, and you watch your breath out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, how would it bring any understanding?
[SPEAKER_02]: At most, that will make you experience certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, a novelty experience of your body in this shape, or that form, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that has nothing to do with discerning and understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because in order to discern and understand, you need to know what you're supposed to discern and understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I tell you, observe your act of breathing, seeing it as impermanent, seeing it as cause of suffering, well, that's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not really a technique, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't say to somebody, oh, I'll try to understand things being given beforehand, which is the reason for you not being able to own them in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't present that as a technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can say it, it can make sense to you, you can attend things like that, but that's the most that it can be.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it doesn't need to be anything more than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know, I know for a fact lots of people get upset.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you dismiss the techniques or whatever, you say, oh, the techniques have been helping me or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: You, as a pathogena, have no criteria of what help is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your criteria is, it feels good, feels better.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, absolutely, the first step is to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you'll know how to meditate.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you don't have the right view, then your meditation should be about getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, when you say this,
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditation is dwelling on the view that you have attained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwelling on my view, dwelling on your right view, is meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but there is other meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are many types of meditation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But only this one is the right one.
[SPEAKER_02]: As the Buddha said himself, I think I spoke there with Arundalina, when he said, you premeditate, overmeditate, undermeditate, mismeditate, and so on, but he doesn't meditate.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he compares it to a dog waiting for a hare, or a jackal, or a cat waiting for a mouse, preying upon something.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's usually what people's meditation is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize, if you look at all these techniques that have been taught, that is actually in common.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all about by observing, observing, looking as close as possible, praying, waiting, waiting, and then it happens.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's all about getting an experience of a novelty kind, anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: And no doubt you will, sooner or later.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because all the all the efforts you're putting in, all the efforts in close observation, all you're going to get is something you get when you look at things closer.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if that's all that's required for wisdom, and nibbāna and understanding, you wouldn't need the Buddha to tell you how to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you know, the whole formulation of the dhamma in like a great great detail and so on, none of that would be necessary then for anyone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because all you have to do is just look at things closer.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you look at things closer, as a patrujana, with your ignorance, all you're doing is looking closer at your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And no knowledge can arise from that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because people sometimes think, oh, you just need to drop everything, just sit and be like a baby still, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't judge, just go back to the whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Primordial state, and that will teach you what you need to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through and through.
[SPEAKER_02]: Experience, we talked about being affected by avijjā.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means whatever you choose to stay with in your experience, will be affected by that avijjā.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is corrupted for putuṣṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I said, you can't accidentally step outside of your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because a repetition is required.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in order to know that the repetition of something will be... is the right thing to get you out of ignorance, you need to be told.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you need to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And doing is not just sitting and staring and waiting for things to teach you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because things are affected with ignorance as much as you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they're part of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, everything, top to bottom, is affected with the vijjā.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even when you sit and meditate like that, all you're going to do will be meditate around your vijjā.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is not accidental that those people, who are very much in technique, would get upset if somebody dismisses their techniques.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would you get upset?
[SPEAKER_02]: Satipaṭṭhāna can't get upset if somebody disparages the dhamma or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: He will say, oh, well, he will clearly know that person doesn't know what they're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it wouldn't upset him.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just impossible to take it personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say that also that the the only... if you're not a self-punisher, doing all sorts of techniques, well, okay, it doesn't matter, but the best thing you can do, which is a kind of meditation in a way, is like...
[SPEAKER_01]: They are trying to understand, trying to dwell on the suttas and go through them, to understand each point so thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a meditation in the proper sense of word.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reflecting with your own experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, like even the first jhāna, which is, well, that's the meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or as the Annāmalai Thera translated it, thinking and exploration of the right things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just, it's just basically being...
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you meditate or not, it's... whether... when I say meditate, whether you sit down, cross-legged or whatever, whichever posture you prefer, you're doing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're pursuing the right view and then the principles of the right view, of the right insight.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can do it more actively or more passively, but it's still the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you get the right view, then you can sit and practice samatha.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't mean forgetting about your right view and observing your kneecaps and shoulders on top of your head and roof of your mouth and nostrils and your lungs.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you can observe those things correctly from the saḷāyātana point of view and then see how your body is just a composure of equal external elements as the objects around you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: upon which you directly stand as your mind, your personality, and everything else, and then disown it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because eyes, roof of your mouth, shoulder, kneecaps, is all given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: What I was saying before.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, your life, as you know it, your past, your future, is inconceivable to be inseparable, to be independent of this living body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this living body, less than two meters tall,
[SPEAKER_02]: Full of organs, like a, like a, like a, you know, sack of, sack of beans tied at the top with just different types inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the necessary cause, necessary condition for your whole life.
[SPEAKER_02]: All emotions, everything you've been through, everything you will go through.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't conceive it if there's not a living body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, if that body comes to die, everything comes to an end, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you recognize that you have no input over that body.
[SPEAKER_02]: No say, no control over it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any control you can exhibit is like what I spoke before.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a movement along the given lines.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before, they were given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you realize your whole life, whatever you've done, whatever you've chosen to do, your volition, it's all determined by this external thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because of it, over which you have no say.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, you can't ask for better meditation than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get that insight, get that thought, and then dwell on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dwell on it, dwell on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the repetition I was talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where meditation leads to wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not where meditation leads to some mystical novelty states.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I felt this trembling, or that trembling, I felt so peaceful, I felt this, I felt that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you get understanding at the end of your meditation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Lots of people don't have that kind of ahma, I might give myself that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're sitting and to go and go watch a thought or think about a subject, what seems to be better for the person is writing it out and actually writing things, not for publication, but actually writing that out, describing it as I see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, that's what I think I should be doing with, obviously, with my... because as I'm doing that writing,
[SPEAKER_01]: I have to bring those, that... You have to dwell on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to dwell on it until, yeah, until it crystallizes to the extent that you're able to put it into words.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't just let it, like, skim over, just... because you don't stop to kind of clarify anything for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just clarifying, but it's difficult, because your mind is skipping this way, that way...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, because you're not used to clarifying the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So your meditation should enable you to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not accidental that meditation results in stillness of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means clarity increases, the mind is jumping less.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you look at things more clearly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, it's the same things you're trying to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: People have this notion whereby, okay, you know, you're trying to study, you contemplate, you reflect, and now it's a time for formal meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you don't do that, you do formal meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is formal meditation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sitting down with your robot.
[SPEAKER_02]: Following a technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is formal like watching your breath or whatever?
[SPEAKER_02]: But why do you do all of that in the first place?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And who knows the way that leads you out of suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why don't you spend all of your time you have trying to become a sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you will know how to meditate and what to do and how to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is, but I notice as well, like I struggle to do breath meditation, but, you know, I try to do it, but then I don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind wanders off, whatever, but if I write about it, I end up being calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, because then I bring it in front of me, and that's the way I'm holding it all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm doing it without doing it the traditional way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: By writing about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Traditional way is the ignorant way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the tradition is written by people, by fukujiners, by people who are not on the way to become arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's not just an empty dismissal.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just that if you look at it and
[SPEAKER_02]: People who compile commentaries and everything, they themselves said they were proficient.
[SPEAKER_02]: Famous commentaries and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: You read assertives, even the techniques were such a crucial factor.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why they wouldn't ever talk about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why there is not a single technique?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something I've got to notice as well, like, the recent... a...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what I can understand, or what I can intellectually comprehend, is that, recently, the arahants, later on, didn't write any commentaries, or didn't do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the kundalinas that kept on writing things and adding things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that they noticed that there's no need
[SPEAKER_02]: More than enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if anything, all of the stuff that's been written later on, the religion is now obscuring those things, because it's been written so long ago, that now people think it to be the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, you read the suttas and all the Buddha talks about all the time is understanding, developing understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, parī, full understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: It always results in full understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever approach of the practice you take, full understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: What full understanding you get from having a mystical experience, it overwhelms you.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's absolutely no understanding there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not even mindfulness often.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, discernment, knowing the cause of suffering, like, knowing the gratification, knowing the escape,
[SPEAKER_02]: In regard to sensuality, in regard to various mental states, knowing the origin, knowing the gratification, knowing the escape, like knowing, like really fully understanding, not analyzing, not getting all the facts, but fully understanding, penetrating with your mind, knowing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all... that's what it's all about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding the nature of things results in freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm going back to my earlier question that, if I say, with the current state of mind, if I'm being reflective about my thoughts and my actions, and if I'm trying to be as mindful as possible, is that meditation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, obviously, be mindful as possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, the better you know what mindfulness is, the more established in mindfulness you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not just a state you emulate, you also want to understand what is presence of mind, what is the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: What else appears there when I think unmindful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Manly ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, manly ignorance or ignorance of what?
[SPEAKER_02]: What you see directly, you don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you want to... you always... you want to be... you want to be like investigating at the same time, not just kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: When you sit and meditate, again, you want to meditate to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't get the right view accidentally, so you can't just sit and be mindful of here and now, present moment, and then learn from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way you can learn from it is if you know what you're supposed to learn, if you know what you're supposed to look for in things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, it's just... you're just staying with your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you'll be as ignorant on the thousandth day as you were on a day one.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, reading the suttas, and then if you want to sit and meditate, like, read the suttas, and then there will be a path that will kind of make sense to an extent, or at least seem promising that you might go.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is something to this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I could... What is it meant?
[SPEAKER_02]: I could perhaps understand this better.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then take that to your meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then dwell on it, in that sense that Tanya was saying.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't just let it, you know, slip or slide.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you need to, you write it down or whatever, but you want to clarify it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the thing, like, you know, I remember when I was doing work meditations on Agarika a lot, and you kind of just, you know, spondering on the suttas and various things, and I might have said this many times before, and, you know, like the five aggregates, and then you just think about the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then it occurred to me, well,
[SPEAKER_02]: When I read the suttas that say consciousness or they talk about matter or feelings, why do I think that I understood by default what consciousness refers to?
[SPEAKER_02]: What feelings refer to?
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever other aggregate that Buddha mentions, why do I... why did I assume that I know what that refers to?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I suddenly think, okay, so what is the matter then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I explain to myself what rūpa is, in my experience, right here, right now, while I'm explaining it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I went like that for every, every aggregate.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize that you don't really have a clear idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just assumed.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just picked up and you have a vague kind of ambiguous, concocted concept of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you stop and think, okay, when I say consciousness-consciousness, or if I say feeling-feeling, what does that exactly stand for?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a clarity there?
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you realize, well, that's what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Undoing all these wrong views, and wrong concepts, and misconceptions, and misperceiving the things that you just took for granted now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now, when even you come... even when you come to practice,
[SPEAKER_02]: The the stuff you read in the suttas, well, you approach it with same polluted concepts, tools, not understood things, that you never questioned.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just start building on top of them, your practice of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's no wonder you end up following weird, various, intense techniques, searching after, preying upon, like those animals in the suttas, that the Buddha says, they prey upon its prey, wait for it, for novelty states, for mystical experiences to take you over,
[SPEAKER_02]: As a form of validation or confirmation of what you've been doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, your whole spiritual life would be misdirected, because you never actually re-evaluated the very kind of basics.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you did, if you did, if you were, then you would realize, oh, the practice is actually in a completely different direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the direction of undoing, so that things can be recognized correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in finding out and rediscovering of something, like something has been obscured and then you just... No, it's... well, it was obscured, you can say it was obscured, by your own misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to be able that when you say to yourself, feeling, feeling, that statement, that designation stands directly for that which feeling is in your experience right there and then.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is not that clarity, there you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a work laid out for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can specifically take feelings, because craving is regard to feelings, and that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Learning how to feel and overcoming the feeling, thus never ever again experiencing suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: The way I said, my teaching is for the one who feels, and he teaches only two things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suffering and freedom for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually where I find a little bit of an advantage
[SPEAKER_00]: You get closer, closer to the meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, when you kind of, you know, you look at the Pali, you learn the Pali, then you look at different translations, different angles.
[SPEAKER_02]: That all becomes necessary, but not for a scholastic purpose, but for the purpose of clarifying.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you see, it's not about, again, finding out some divine providence, a mystical light.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's about undoing your wrong views, so that you recognize what the right view is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when it comes to undoing, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to have as clear as possible instructions, so you'll know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the utterance of another.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the Buddha's not around anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, actually, even when he was, he referred to a miracle of instruction.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, being able to convey the dhamma to somebody, and they fully understand it, and then become arahant or khandhā, equals to a miracle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why, Beth, when you see yourself?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because we all take things and terminology to mean, you know, sometimes completely, sometimes slightly different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even a slight variation in what it means for me, when I utter it for him, can be quite a lot at the end of the line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, imagine a boat or a ship is setting on a course, and in the beginning, you know, it doesn't matter if it's a meter to the left, a meter to the right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But after, you know, thousands of miles of journey, that tiny little kind of variation will result in missing a whole continent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why you want to get as much, because you don't have a criteria what's right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to try to clarify for yourself as much as you can.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you kind of decrease the chances of being wrong later on, or at least not go too far off.
[SPEAKER_01]: I like the, what's it, the concept of mindfulness, the thinking of mindfulness, what that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's thinking about it, clarifying that, which is quite helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you can look at things better.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can try to do certain things better once you know how to be mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But... Because most people, most people, most people think, oh, I can be mindful, I just mean being here and now, present.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: Vinaya, you... Well, exactly, because when you... you realize, yeah, you can be mindful, but if you have lots of wrong views, you'll be mindful with your wrong views.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's actually quite true.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you take an average person sort of being mindful, if you were to ask them to describe it, well... well, first of all, they probably wouldn't be able to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But second, it will all revolve around the wrong views of... as if I'm in the present moment, as if the present moment is sort of...
[SPEAKER_02]: In a constant change, constant flux that I step into, just through reminding myself of mindfulness, then also another belief comes that, well, if I just have enough, a sufficient amount of my mindful mind moments, then I'll be, I'll reach nibbāna automatically or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you realize, well, mindfulness is obviously the absolute necessity.
[SPEAKER_02]: But
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're not knowing where to, how to undo your avijjā, all you're going to be mindful is, or rather, whatever you're mindful of, will be mindful of with your avijjā.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be ignorant in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, mindfulness needs to... well, mindfulness and authenticity, like self-transparency, being honest to yourself, is the first step.
[SPEAKER_02]: These one, the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're genuinely mindful, the first thing you're going to recognize is, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: The second thing you can come to sort of recognize is, well, okay, what do I need to know then?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you sort of start to narrow it down.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to know everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need to know suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's where your mindfulness should also be concerned with.
[SPEAKER_02]: With your feeling, what feeling is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then it will become apparent that actually,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, for example, as I mentioned, the idea of the the idea of the flux, the idea of how everything is constantly changing, doesn't make sense, because if everything's constantly changing, there wouldn't be any change at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you're mindful, there is something, your experience is present as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's mindful, it's enduring, which means, if you were to then say, oh, it's constantly changing, or any other wrong view of that kind, that would mean you're adopting an external explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That it's not validated by your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your mindfulness tells you the contrary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means you then ignore your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: To explain it based on the views that you accepted beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then you want to stop doing that, really, and then develop mindfulness, and then the views that come from what's evident in your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was the whole idea of phenomenology.
[SPEAKER_02]: The, like, the philosophical movement of essential philosophy is basically describing only what's what's evident in a phenomenological outlook, which is the mindful outlook, mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if anything else would fall off, no matter how plausible it was, they would recognize it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's an explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if it's an explanation, means it's not actually coming from the direct mindfulness, direct description, direct understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: As such, it can be accepted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, phenomenologists and essential philosophers couldn't
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, arrive at greater conclusions, but it's a valid method.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, in that case, in that, if you were to do it, you can't, like, you know, you can go off the tracks a bit, left to right, but you can't go off too far.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because this principle of being based upon mindfulness is not abandoned.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it will always bring you back and restart.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that means person will have to be willing to completely let go, challenge, abandon his own most personal views.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, let alone not get angry over it, or upset, or argumentative.
[SPEAKER_02]: But really, genuinely, whenever he approaches to the new view, or to the view that sort of challenges his own view, he approaches it with a sense as something that might be right, and it might... has to be accepted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means that what he has now,
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it's years of practice invested, are always in question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you do it like that, then the solid core will actually remain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will be abandoning everything unnecessary, everything wrong, while the right things will stay there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they were right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not easy.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you know, it comes to a point whereby
[SPEAKER_02]: You experience fear by reading different views, by reading views that are challenging yours, by talking to people that are saying you're wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like genuine existential anxiety, fear.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not optional, holding views.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not optional.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, views are what you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of your own foundation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, challenging them feels like you're really shaking your own foundations.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you get angry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's why most people get angry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you say our meditation techniques are nonsense.
[SPEAKER_02]: How dare you say that?
[SPEAKER_02]: I've been meditating for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, good for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do you get angry on account of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Meditation is supposed to free you from greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why are you getting angry now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of your meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a contradiction in turn.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you either haven't been meditating rightly, since you're not free from anger, or the Buddha was wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, which one it is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we all know which one it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I recognize that I don't have any mindfulness, and in order to develop it, if I keep reflecting as much as I can, like, as the moment passes,
[SPEAKER_00]: See, there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: One moment passes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not one moment passes, but more like the moment that I passed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reflect, keep reflecting, like, on my actions, like, as fast as I can.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, again, it's fast.
[SPEAKER_02]: What?
[SPEAKER_02]: You're chasing something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are things moving now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you don't see them immediately, are they gone?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you think of them then, even as gone, if they were gone?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if I can only...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't really recognize it as being arising, but just... What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you can't see the point of origin, I think, if you can only find it as originated, what is there to chase?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would you have to be fast, in any way?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's persisting there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I call that a mindfulness or is that just a reflection?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's mindful reflection.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inseparable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sati, recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sati, sampajañña, mindfulness and awareness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sati is the same word used for memory.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the whole, the whole, this whole misconception of kind of observing the external moment, chasing them, being fast, quick, grasping.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a completely misguided view.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's truly past, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even think about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even speak about it in a past tense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact that you can, means it's not gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means it still persists, while it's changing on some levels.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You recognize the stillness within the particular movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: You stay with the stillness, you're mindful of the movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you go after a movement, well, you're pulverized, you're done.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, the simile in the sutra is a man who needs to keep an eye on, I don't know, twenty, thirty, I don't know, five dozen of children.
[SPEAKER_02]: He can't possibly go around chasing after every one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: If he does, he'll exhaust himself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if he doesn't, he can see only one at a time, the one that he is chasing, which means the other forty-nine children
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he recognizes that, instead of chasing individually, he finds a slightly elevated ground from which he can see them all at once.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he's not particularly involved with any one of them, but he can see them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if one of them goes too far, he calls them back.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's like the basic practice of mindfulness, which is the practice of meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no samatha, there is no meditation of any kind without mindfulness as a foundation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically sitting down.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can, I don't know, be mindful of your breathing if you want, but don't sweat it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: But be mindful what you're thinking while you're sitting down, while you're seated, to be more precise.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, don't try to be kind of chasing your thoughts of growth, seeing where they originate, or look for every moment of your thoughts, because they will assume you being external to your own thoughts, or your thoughts external to it, but you are your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, once you're mindful of them as what has arisen, or these thoughts are present, leave it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just don't, don't, don't, don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Try kind of holding it tightly, trying to see every, like, microscopic moment, because there is no such thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's an assumption.
[SPEAKER_02]: What you have is, such thought is present, then another thought is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't want to interfere with it directly, but you don't want to lose sight of it completely.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, you don't want to be chasing all those children all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to step back, so that you can see them more, more of them, without...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not chasing them directly, but you're not not looking at them either.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the attitude you want to have towards your own mind, your own thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you sit down and meditate, let things arise, don't interfere with it, because it's nothing to do with you in the first place, but then don't lose the sight of it completely.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a practice in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practice of mindfulness, practice of meditation, practice that can bring the discernment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, although even as a practitioner, you can be emulating things rightly, and if you emulate it long enough, it will lead to the right results.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, keeping a peripheral sight, keeping a corner of your eye on your thoughts, is basically how you establish yourself in mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: That allows other things to rise, persist while they change, in front of you directly, but at the back of your mind, there is still a corner of the eye looking at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like a peripheral vision, and you don't stare at things directly in order to see them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can use the example of a, like a bouncer, you stand by the gate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, look at the guard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, there is a sutra, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't go into, you don't have to look for a person and check... Because you know, you know, you figure out, you understand beforehand, that whoever comes in, whoever goes out, will have to come through here.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all you have to do, just stay there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whoever came in, you don't go after them, you know they're in.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all I need to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whoever goes out, you know, they're out.
[SPEAKER_02]: If something, there is a temptation that pulls you, wants you to go in, well, you resist that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you know, well, if I leave this entry point, this door, this sole entry point, I will lose the sight of everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't leave that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like mindfulness of the feelings, or mindfulness of the nature of your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means you don't have to be
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindful and concerned with every particular thought for as long as you're mindful of the thought is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense with the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, to be mindful of the body internally, externally, internally, externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindful of this, mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: All he's mindful of the body is there to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even such a general thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, body is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: He sees that always peripherally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the body is always there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever situation you're in, good or bad, neutral, left or right, up or down, your body is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Peripherally, you know, you... 99% of your attention can be taken by whatever else, but in that distant peripheral distance, there is still recognition, there is still knowledge, body is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's your anchor of your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means that these 99% cannot actually take you away.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cannot overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there's still that 1% anchored properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what anchor is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You throw an anchor, you let it sink, and then you forget about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a sense that you're not constantly pulling it up and throwing it in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pulling it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's pointless.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what meditation techniques end up doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, just get back to the moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get back to the moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get back to the present moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: You get back to the present moment when you completely forgot about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get back to it so that you can let it go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let it take its course while you remain slightly anchored in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I peripherally keep an eye on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you throw an anchor and then you let the boat float away.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when an anchor is established properly, the boat will not float away too far, or it will float away as far as the anchor allows it to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the common contemporary techniques, basically, would translate into throwing an anchor, then pulling it out, then throwing an anchor, then pulling it out, for the sake of doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can never ever get a concept of mindfulness, concept of things enduring, persisting, work changing, movement within thing that is still.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're constantly just, just, just joking left and right, just throwing, throwing, throwing, throwing.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's this, what's bending is the best still point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, because even, even just trying to think about what the body is,
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of can lose ground, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, different times are different.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why there's so many, like different foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you're saying, like also what you said about experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't come across that term in the suttas with body, feelings, and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I hear experience as a whole, and I see that God, the experience as a whole, what is happening now,
[SPEAKER_01]: That phenomenon of our experience as a whole, it seems to be easier to... Again, I think that just depends on the person, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even within the same person, sometimes you'll need to do different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes, you know, like the habit of ignorance will still prevail and then you'll end up just like not getting the same answer you have to.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why there's so many different approaches, different types.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes, just to refresh your mind, you would take a different approach.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes, a different approach would make more sense than the previous approach.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, the principles of those approaches remain the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: The principle of mindfulness, the principle of understanding, the principle of determinations, all of that remains the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, it doesn't really matter what particular manifestation of that principle you're engaging in.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as you're aiming at the principle, it's all contributing towards the same understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what I... why I like that experience with holes as well is because I can't doubt that I'm experiencing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I can doubt, is this my body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that my body?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that my...
[SPEAKER_02]: But the body is there, you can't doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because all of these movements in regard to that body, is this, is this, or is that, is that, it's possible only because that body is arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once, yeah, once you come
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, as, like, as experience as a whole, watching that, nothing else, nothing's going to happen without it happening within that experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, guarding the experience you thought you... And once you get used to guarding it, then you can start making the effort within that and discerning it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within that experience as a whole, what is feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say feeling, feeling, what does that stand within that experience as a whole that I'm already mindful of?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're creating, like, a ground on which you can start doing the work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it has to be something.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you're referring to feeling, feeling, what does that designation stand for?
[SPEAKER_02]: What does it aim at?
[SPEAKER_02]: What does it signify?
[SPEAKER_02]: And you want to clarify that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean I'm...
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that means you're doubting what's wholesome, what's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're paying attention to figure out if it's wholesome or unwholesome, it means you don't know if it's wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what you want to do is develop criteria of your mindfulness, whereby recognizing being mindful of something will already know if what you're mindful of is wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the criteria would be the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, reflection of an action to be wholesome or unwholesome has to happen at a different time?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it can happen through that, for as long as you don't deceive yourself into thinking that you already know what's wholesome and what's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only a person with the right view knows wholesome as wholesome, unwholesome as unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's that sūtra again, the two types of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's... the Buddha did... well, the previous... well, he's not the Buddha yet, but he divides his thoughts into two parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is, thoughts connected with ill-will, greed, delusion...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cruelty.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cruelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, thoughts connected to non-ill will, non-cruelty and renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, he reflects, is this what I am doing good for me, good for another?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it bring about wisdom?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, or is it not good for me, not good for another?
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to show it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he reflects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, through those questions, that kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he knows that, oh, this is... this is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: This doesn't disturb me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't disturb anyone else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm... my understanding is developing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the criteria you can trust, even in the Putujan.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can see that none of the techniques you will be doing, in terms of meditation, would come under that.
[SPEAKER_02]: What wisdom you're developing by watching your nostrils.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes you feel good.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, really, it comes down to discernment, mental discernment, something that you cannot put into a method.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you need to constantly, oh, is what I'm doing, what I'm thinking, would that be harmed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Does that imply, is that connected to harming others, harming me, harming both, harming neither?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, it doesn't seem it's harming neither.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, is it also making me discern things?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it making things clearer?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when I say feeling-feeling or when I say perception-perception, do I know where those things stand for clearer?
[SPEAKER_02]: And the reason why I'm singling these things out is because those things are the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the five aggregates are the ones affected with assumptions, with the wrong views, with upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even in your speech, in designation, that's all form of upādāna can be, if it stands for wrong things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It expresses the wrong things, the wrong assumptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to have things clear for you, not explained, not laid out, like as a nice little tidy chart, a map of things, oh, this is what it is, this is what it is, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to know exactly when you utter a designation, you know what it stands for, phenomenologically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I reckon.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what it means, like, developing discernment, developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you have to keep thinking like that, because if you are, well, you would at least be striving in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't see that as a criteria, developing that kind of wisdom, then, exactly, then you can, yeah, well, watching, watching my nostrils doesn't harm anyone, doesn't harm me, doesn't harm others, so it's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not developed wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, exactly, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when it comes to developing wisdom and understanding, there is no method you can engage in, as I said before.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: To each individual.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's to... it's to each individual, and it's also... understanding and discernment of the nature of things precedes the designation, the nature of designation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can hear the instruction, but then you're understanding what it pertains to.
[SPEAKER_02]: You perceive it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the Buddha referred to it as miracle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that connection is something, through your own efforts, can become apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're solely responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, even this instruction, utterance of another, can go only so far.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, me designating you a set of methods and observances you go through, and then you just adhering to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But can that somehow magically lead you onto that connection that you yourself responsible connection of understanding?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a fetter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sīlabhātaparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Holding on to virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, people translate that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sīlabhātaparamāsa is holding on to rites and rituals.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereby, it means, oh, rites and rituals.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's kind of obvious.
[SPEAKER_02]: We all know that, you know, bowing to the random stone shrine doesn't mean anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we all abandon that fetter.
[SPEAKER_02]: We just do it for whatever reasons, but we know it's not the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, the pala is sīlabhāta-paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sīla is the virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sīlabhāta-paramāsa means holding on to the sense of virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_02]: And basically,
[SPEAKER_02]: Holding on to thinking that your sīla, your purity, your valid, genuine purity, is what practice is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Holding on to your sense of duty as somebody who practices the Buddha's teaching, or I should be doing this, I should be meditating, I should be... Holding on to that to be the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that is a fattah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's not the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they did say, there is no dhamma without vinaya, but vinaya is not dhamma, and dhamma is not vinaya.
[SPEAKER_02]: But obviously, you need vinaya in order to be able to practice dhamma correction.
[SPEAKER_02]: But dhamma is not vinaya, dhamma is not sīla.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even your precepts that need to be pure, need to be kept, have nothing to do with dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're gonna go like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dhamma is elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you look at it, why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's obvious.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because precepts are something you do, you observe.
[SPEAKER_02]: Techniques are something you do, you perform.
[SPEAKER_02]: But understanding of the nature of things is something you cannot do, you cannot perform.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is a completely different domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, the understanding of the nature of things cannot happen if your behavior has not been purified externally through keeping the precepts and not engaging and maintaining unwholesome things through those bad habits.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that purification through that behavior is not the understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can be as pure as, like, you know, anything that comes, but still not understand things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So there is no guarantee of understanding through following methods, or observances, or duties.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's not what understanding is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's almost like, you know, that does not mean that, oh, I can do whatever I want and get the understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you didn't understand things when things were favorable for you, when you were keeping the precepts, where you're not increasing the greed, aversion, delusion, well, then you're certainly not going to understand when your behavior is increasing greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, it's a necessary prerequisite, but it's not it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can see why then, like, thinking, oh, a certain prescribed technique, oh, can you, Ajahn, can you give me a technique or something I can do that will lead me to, you know, the magical place of Arahantship?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually wrong, very, very seriously wrong view, because it becomes an impediment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you think that you're actually practicing by observing this mechanical technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means that's where your efforts stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't stop and then start reflecting on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: The nature of what you're doing, which is what understanding is.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you're just doing it, just doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just repeating, buddho, buddho, buddho, buddho, like a robot, and that brings me full understanding of stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that brings you the understanding, then the whole Tipiṭaka would be just buddho, buddho, buddho, buddho, buddho, buddho, buddho, wherever you open it, or whatever page you open it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not, not even once.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never the Buddha say you just repeat this mantra, and
[SPEAKER_02]: Many other followers and teachers of different sects and religions said that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they were all mentioned as wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because nothing mechanical, such as repeating Buddha, Buddha, or watching the tip of your nose, can bring understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only thing that can bring understanding is your attitude that's trying to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that attitude can be in regard to anything that is established upon also.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, the meditation techniques, well, they're wrong because people think them, take them to be right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in themselves, they're not even wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're absolutely pointless.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can be watching your nostrils, or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the point?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can watch the tips of your ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the Buddha, when he was teaching, he was talking about these things, certain things, you know, the five aggregates, the five elements, he's talking about those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people understand and get free from substance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they're understanding the designations that he's using when he says.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not ringing a bell.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they will become arahants, right there and then, by listening to the Buddha speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by watching their nose for three hours, and then we go walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, understanding what he's talking about, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually paying attention, trying to figure out... Paying attention to designations that he's using, and then seeing them for what they are, in their own experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: They have the right attitude, trying to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the designations they themselves were operating with were not as polluted as most of other people today's designations are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, it's nothing magical about people becoming arahants upon listening to Buddha speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, you know, the Buddha knew their mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not the reason why they became arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: They became arahants because they understood what he was saying.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if now you don't understand what the Buddha is saying in the suttas, it's because you just have so many obstructions and assumptions of your own doing, for which you're fully responsible, obscuring the meaning of the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, undo your own assumptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Undo your own designations to the extent necessary, whereby you read the suttas and it's directly describing your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: When that's the case, 100% you'll be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because every sutta describes experience of an arahant, or how to become one.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you read a sutta and it seems like common sense, like, oh yeah... Oh, that means you have some serious work to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And yeah, lots of people say, well, this is just common sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just repetition.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you think of it just in terms that I said, imagine
[SPEAKER_02]: If every designation that the Buddha would use stands for a direct description in your experience, then him repeating it through different aspects of it would be bringing it, in your experience, one aspect within the other, within the other, within...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can see it's almost like a natural progression of understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like fortifying it in regard to this, in regard to this, within that, within this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize the suttas are far from just repetitive, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: kind of tautological folklore descriptions of something, it's actually direct phenomenological instruction and like leading on further and further and further in developing of your understanding and your purification of your own designations.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were carrying wrong wrong assumptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you approach it directly, rather correctly, if you approach it correctly, with the right view,
[SPEAKER_02]: And phenomenological mindfulness established, reading the suttas would be like directly purifying your own experience while you're reading them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's what they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, repeating it for 20 times would be 20 repetitions of purifications.
[SPEAKER_02]: 6 times, 12 times, 18 times.
[SPEAKER_02]: No matter how many times it would repeat, you would retreat, and each time it would be a purified image of a correct designation, things standing correctly for what they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, reading the suttas becomes the direct practice, the direct insight, which is how it was when the Buddha was speaking to those who became sotāpannas or arahants upon listening.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why repetition in the suttas, because he's not explaining.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a direct description of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if he repeats it six times in regard to every sense, that's because... that's how it needs to be seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Repetitively, in regard to every sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you leave a sense unturned, ignorance will stay there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, powerful.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we were talking about the other day about jhānas being, you know, by thinking and pondering in the correct way, one enters the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, you're secluded from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're guarding your mind, so you notice, I'm secluded from wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything has to come through here, has to come through here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm restraining my senses, my senses are guarded.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you enter, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: They've become joy and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just... there is no blanking out, ever.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, the sutta, one by one, I think it was 109, Madhyamaka, about Sariputta's, according to different, sort of, establishments of his mind, the first jhāna, second jhāna, third jhāna, and so on, all the way up to cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every of those states had mindfulness present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just fortifying that same mindfulness, which is not, like, completely the opposite of what what people expect to achieve through various meditation techniques, when you're just not aware of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, oh, yeah, I went into this state...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm mindful, and then...
[SPEAKER_02]: I went into this state of neither perception nor perception, because I don't... Gee, it was just this state I entered, and next thing I know, it was five o'clock in the morning.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, yeah, we heard you're neither perception nor perception snoring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or like, oh, yeah, well, I go into this state when I don't hear or see anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good meditation, no?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not according to the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, there are neither perception or perception of genuine kind, cessation of perception and feeling, but in order to get there, your mindfulness has to be utterly, completely unshakable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But a lot of people refer to it as mindfulness as a phenomenon, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, like, you know, I kind of, in the beginning, always giving the benefit of doubt, but then the more they talk about it, you realize you were just asleep, mate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you know when you go in a state when you can't fall asleep because you're not lying down, but you're kind of half out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lots of people end up in that state because they're seated on the floor, so you can't quite fall asleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: The twilight zone.
[SPEAKER_02]: The twilight zone, which again, that jhāna is confirmed by kind of external eye of nodding.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can see them nodding left and right, bobbing and weaving, sort of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, I have a good meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we saw that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, it's the lack of a person being authentic.
[SPEAKER_02]: They lie to themselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, yeah, you know, quite a few people I've met were very sensitive about a topic of meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they would be implying that they're maybe not meditating rightly, or if somebody else would be implying indirectly that what they're doing is not right, they get very upset.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, well, what's the point of your meditation if you hold on to it so dearly?
[SPEAKER_02]: And personally, you're getting upset if somebody criticizes you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And surely, you're not doing it right.
[SPEAKER_02]: If someone else's random view can shake you up so much, can offend you... You should be grateful in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, there you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just laid it out for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, if I read this, Roman philosophers, Greek philosophers, they sought out challenges, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: You sought out a challenge of your view, not the challenge to prove your sīla is good or something like that, which sometimes people do.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to challenge your views.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, someone says, oh, tell me your view... That's the attitude you can be sure about, that can't lead you to wrong, is attitude of challenging every view, no matter how dear to you it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The views are dear to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha said, ah, surely you're holding to that view because it pleases you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's dear to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, when that man said, I said to the Buddha, I don't hold to any views.
[SPEAKER_02]: No views are pleasing to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, well, surely that view is pleasing to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you say, oh, okay, yeah, you have a point there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you have a view, that no view will be dear to you, including that view, in a sense, that whatever view you have, you recognize you always have to have a view.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have a state of no view, because that's a view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, if you believe it's not the view, you're contradicting yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you're even more wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not about not having any views, which is impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's about finding the right view, and then going beyond even the right view, which is possible, which is arahantship.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in order to get the right view, you must not hold to any view for the sake of pleasing you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this view is pleasing to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't help having a view being pleasing to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what you can help is not leaving it unturned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not take it for granted, not leaving it unquestioned.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you get a view, then you find the views that are opposing to that view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you think, oh, this is a wrong view, well, you need to fully understand why, how and where that view is wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just decide this is wrong because somebody else said, even the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, the Buddha said that, well, sure, but do you understand it for yourself?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you understand why wrong views are wrong?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you do, you have the right views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's dang... so it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's probably... well, it is useful if someone... you know, someone who can challenge you, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't have anybody challenging you, then open any... any book.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, challenge yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Open... because you're bound to think, oh, these... these views are wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, open those books, read them, and try to see for yourself why, how and where those views are wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, just assume they're wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: And same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, the Buddha is right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Open the suttas and understand where, how and why it's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you're doing it correctly, you'll see.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be fearful.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be, like, anxious to read other stuff that you think is wrong, because you might not see it is wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you're not as right as you think you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to go through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so let's take the thing that you
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if there is anything right, it's that which cannot be taken personally, and it will stay.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will stay on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't drop off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it can't be... no one can challenge it, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: No one can take it away.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've been challenging it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've been, like, attacking it with doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And whatever was susceptible to doubt was affectable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Except those things that were beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you go beyond doubt by basically reaching a point where the doubt cannot enter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because you were shying away from doubting it, but because you were doubting full on.
[SPEAKER_02]: You fully became doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you recognize that there are points the doubt cannot enter.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's doubt free.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Beyond doubt means inaccessible to doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't mean, oh, I never doubt this because, you know, I fear.
[SPEAKER_02]: I fear that if I doubt, I might change my mind, re-evaluate everything and, phew, 30 years that I invest in this, down the drain.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: From the day one, full on doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very unpleasant, but, you know, relatively quick way of progressing if you do it right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you know, oh, this is beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because I'm not doubting it, but because its nature is impenetrable to doubt.